Preliminary Inventory of the I. G. Duca papers
Hoover Institution Archives
I. G. Duca papers
1914-1933
66009
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 3 microfilm reels (2.7 linear feet)
Memoirs, correspondence, notes, and memoranda, relating to Romanian politics and foreign policy.
Duca, I. G. (Ion George), 1879-1933.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1966.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Memoirs also available on negative microfilm copy.
Biographical/Historical Note
Ion George Duca was prime minister of Romania from November 14 to December 30, 1933, when he was assassinated for his efforts to suppress the fascist Iron Guard movement.
Born in Bucharest on December 20, 1879, he entered Romania's Chamber of Deputies for the National Liberal Party in 1907 and served in the cabinet from 1914. Appointed Minister of Foreign Affairs in 1922, he was an avid supporter of the Little Entente, an alliance formed between Romania, Yugoslavia, and Czechoslovakia.
In November, 1933, King Carol II of Romania asked Duca to head the government as prime minister in preparation for the December elections. What followed was a time of violence when police jailed thousands of Iron Guard members. Shortly after the release of many of the Iron Guard members from jail, Duca was shot on the platform of the Sinaia train station by Nicolae Constantinescu.
Ion George Duca's extensive political memoirs were edited by his son George while at the Hoover Institution at Stanford University in the 1970s and 1980s.
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, correspondence, notes, and memoranda, relating to Romanian politics and foreign policy.
Romania--Foreign relations.; Romania--History--1914-1944.; Romania--Politics and government--1914-1944.; Statesmen--Romania.; World War, 1914-1918--Romania.
- Negatives of the pictures published in the three volumes of I.G. Duca's political memoirs., 1981-1982 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Aminitiri Politice
  - Neutralitatea
    - Chp 1: Vinerea la putere (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Chp 2: Cele dintai 6 luni (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Chp 3: Vizita Tarului la Constanta (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Chp 4: Izbucnirea razboiului general (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Chp 5: Consiliul de Coroana dela Sinaia (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Chp 6: Ultimele luni ale dominiei Regelui Carol (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Chp 7: Moartea Regelui Carol - Portretul Regelui Carol (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Chp 8: Inceptul nouii domnii (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Chp 9: Regele Ferdinand - Regina Maria (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Chp 10: Iarna, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Chp 11: Primavara 1915 - Intrarea Italiei in razboi (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Chp 12: Zvarcolirile opozitiei - Victoriile germane (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Chp 13: Incidentul Poklewski (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Chp 14: Toamna, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Chp 15: Iarna, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Chp 16: Sesiunea parlamentara, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Chp 17: Primavara 1916 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Chp 18: Precipitarea evenimentelor (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Chp 19: Bratianu se hotareste (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Chp 20: Iscapirea tratatului (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Chp 21: Ultimele zile ale neutralitaii (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Chp 22: Consiliul de Coroana dela Cotroceni - Declararea razboiului (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Chp 23: Moartea Reginei Elisabeta (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Razboiul
    - Chp 24: Razboiul - Primele zile (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Chp 25: Desperarea lui Bratianu - Mantuau lui Arvintie (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Chp 26: Apararea in Carpati - Moartea lui Filipescu (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Chp 27: Chinuitoarele alternative - Moartea Principelui Mircea (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Chp 28: Dezastrul se precipita - Falkenhayn trece Carpatii si Mackensen Dunarea (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Chp 29: Batalia pentru apararea Bucurestilor - Ultime zile (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Chp 30: Iasi - Primele saptamani (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Pencil used by Duca to write memoirs (Envelope 3: 1)
    - Chp 31: Ultimele saptamani ale anuilui 1916 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Chp 32: Primele luni tifosul exantemantic, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Chp 33: Primele luni, uxmare - Revolutia ruseasca - Intrarea Americei (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Chp 34: Refomele - Partidul muncii (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Chp 35: Bolsevismul (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Chp 36: Criza ministeriala - Ofensiva pe Siret - Marasti, Marasesi (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Chp 37: August - Septembre (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Chp 38: Dela venirea lui Lenin la putere pana la dezarmarea trupelor rusesti in Moldova (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Chp 39: Noaptea dela 9 Decembre - Dezarmarea bolsevicilor - Lichidarea frontului resesc, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Chp 40: Dela dezarmarea bolsevicilor la demisia guvernului (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - Chp 41: Guvernul Averescu (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - Chp 42: Guvernul Marghiloman (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Chp 43: Ostracizatii (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Chp 44: Desnodamantul (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - Chp 45: Guvernarea noastra - Conferinta pacii, Novembre 1918-1919 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Diverse
    - Chp 46: Moartea Regelui Ferdinand, Moartea lui Ion I. C. Bratinanu, Moartea lui Vintila Bratianu. (Box-folder 3: 17)
- Callimacki, Anne Marie. "Jean Marie." (Box-folder 3: 18)
- Sample of Ion G. Duca's handwriting (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Correspondence
  - Bibesco, Prince (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Cantacuzino, Dr. I., 1917 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Dobrogeanu-Gherea, A., 1917 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Ghitescu, P. (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Grigorcea, G., 1919 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Lapedatu, A., 1917 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Lupescu, General (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Mitilineu, Ion M., 1920 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Murgoci, Professor G., 1919 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Stefanescu, Professor M., 1919 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 4: 12)
- Subject Files
  - Callings cards from prominent persons (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Concert program on the occassion of Tsar Nicholas II's visit to the Romanian Court in 1914 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Duca, Jean: letter regarding the situation during the German occupation., 1917-1918 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Kerguezec, A. de (French senator): legal case of land expropriation., 1924-1925 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Letters to the Foreign Secretary from parents regarding tehir diplomat sons, 1922 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Lausanne Peace Conference, 1922-1923
    - Congratulatory messages to I. Duca (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - French Delegation: a letter to the Romanian Foreign Secretary (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Helen, Crown Princess of Romania: telegram to I. Duca. (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - Invitations and notes (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - Invitation to a private audience and luncheon with the King of Italy (Box-folder 4: 22)
    - List of various military and political personnel I. Duca visited (Box-folder 4: 23)
    - Mussolini, B., luncheon invitation from. (Box-folder 4: 24)
    - Notes on I. Duca's conversations with Lord Curzon (head of the British Delegation) and Imset Pacha (head of the Turkish Delegation) (Box-folder 4: 25)
    - Small list of gifts for several members of the foreign delegations (Box-folder 4: 26)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - Rumania Ministry of Foreign Affairs
    - Ion Duca announces to a political friend the resignation of the liberal government, March 26, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 28)
    - Letters from various foreign chiefs of missions in Bucharest regarding I. Duca's departure from the Foreign Office, March-April 1926 (Box-folder 4: 29)
    - Nintchiich, N. (Yugoslav Foreign Secretary): letter to I. Duca., April 4, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 30)
    - Telegrams in Ion Duca's handwriting, March 29, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 31)
    - Various Romanian chiefs of missions thanking I. Duca for his farewell message to them, March 29, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 32)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 4: 33)
- Diary. Relates to Lausanne Peace Conference., 1922 (Box-folder 4: 34-37)
- Microfilm Reels (Reel 1-3)
  Includes two reels of the Duca's diary related to Lausanne Peace Conference in 1922.
- Rest of collection not yet described (Boxes 5-6)